A Guide to the Papers of The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry 1934-2001
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- CNHI: The Gloria K. Nuckles Papers 1950-1953, 1 box, .4 linear feet
  - Series 1: Nursing Coursework
    - Microbiology 195o (Box-folder 001-003)
    - Anatomy & Physiology 1950 (Box-folder 001-004)
    - Anatomy & Physiology 1950 (Box-folder 001-005)
    - Pharmacology 1950 (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Examinations & Booklet, "Therapeutic Use of Cortone".
    - Medical Terminology 1950 (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Student nurses tests & notes.
    - Chemistry 1950 (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Notes & tests.
    - Nutrition 1951 (Box-folder 001-009)
    - Gynecology 1951 (Box-folder 001-010)
    - Surgical Nursing 1952 (Box-folder 001-011)
    - Pediatrics 1952 (Box-folder 001-012)
    - Nursing Arts/Professional Adjustments 1951 (Box-folder 001-013)
      Re: Student nurse notes & tests.
    - Communicable Disease 1951 (Box-folder 001-014)
      Re: Student nurse's classroom notes & booklet, "Supplement to Control of Com. Dis, Department of Health, Va., 1951."
    - Obstetrics 1952 (Box-folder 001-015)
      Re: Student nurse classroom notes.
    - Psychiatry 1953 (Box-folder 001-016)
      Re: Notes & tests taken at Eastern State Hospital, Williamsburg, Virginia.
- CNHI: Gretchen Osgood Collection 1963 - 1990, 3 boxes, 1.5 linear feet
  This collection consists primarily of government publications containing data from numerous nursing surveys. For the most part, these studies concern nursing education and manpower, and legal issues related to the health professions. The collection also contains a 1979 original manuscript on the history of nurse practitioners and miscellaneous other publications, letters, and articles on nursing collected by Ms. Osgood. These materials range in date from the 1960s through the 1990s.
  Series Description: The collection has been arranged into three chronological series: Series 1: Nursing Manpower and Education, Series 2: Health Professions Legislation, Series 3: Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice.
  - Series 1: Nursing Manpower and Education
    - Nursing Manpower and Education (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Toward Quality in Nursing: Needs and Goals (Feb. 1963); Toward Quality in Nursing: Needs and Goals (Feb. 1963, reprinted May, 1963); Backtalk: In Defense of the Report of the Surgeon General's Consultant Group on Nursing; ANA Position Paper: Educational Preparation of Nurses.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: ANA letter: Sound Planning for Nursing Education & attached handwritten note; Nurse Training Act of 1964: Program Review Report (Dec. 1967, reprinted 1970).
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: First Report to the Congress: Nurse Training Act of 1975; Third Report to the Congress: Nurse Supply, Distribution and Requirements
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Nursing and Nursing Education: Public Policies and Private Actions/ Institute of Medicine Report.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: ANA Press Release regarding IOM Report; IOM Report Supports Education Funding (The American Nurse); Did the Education Commission Say Anything (The Brookings Review); The Response of the Western Council on Higher Education for Nursing to the National Studies on Nursing.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Fifth Report to the Congress on the Status of Health Personnel in the United States: August, 1985; Fifth Report to the President and Congress on the Status of Health Personnel in the United States.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Cost Estimating Model for Baccalaureate Nursing Education Programs; Presentation to the Division on Nursing Health Resources and Services Administration: A Cost Estimating Model for Baccalaureate Nursing Education Programs.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: American Journal of Nursing Supplement: Nurses for the Future: A provocative debate on economics, enrollment and essentials; The Dignity of Nursing by George Will (Newsweek); Responses to George Will article.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: Sixth Report to the President and Congress on the Status of Health Personnel in the United States; Secretary's Commission on Nursing Interim Report, Volume III; Thank you letter to Ms. Osgood from the Secretary's Commission on Nursing.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education (Continued from Box 1 (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Secretary's Commission on Nursing: Support Studies and Background Information, Volume II.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Secretary's Commission on Nursing: Final Report; Flexible Models of Nursing Education (book chapter).
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Seventh Report to the President and Congress on the Status of Health Personnel in the United States.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: The Registered Nurse Population: Findings from the National Sample Survey of Registered Nurses, March 1988.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Final Report: Evaluation of Nursing Education Projects.
    - Nursing Manpower and Education, cont'd. (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Commission on the National Nursing Shortage: Final Report; Survey of Beneficiaries.
  - Series 2 & 3: Health Professions Legislation, Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice.
    - Health Professions Legislation: Publications (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: Chronology Health Professions Legislation 1956-1979; Supplement to Chronology Health Professions Legislation covering laws enacted through 1980; Chronology of Federal Support for Program of Nursing Education and Research Administered by the Division of Nursing.
    - Health Professions Legislation: Publications, cont'd. (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Highlight Summary of Title XXVIII of PL97-35, Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1981; Amendments of Special Interest to BHPr (Bureau of Health Professions), Orphan Drug Act; Public Laws Authorizing BHPr Programs (78th to 95th Congress); Public Laws Authorizing BHPr Programs (96th Congress to date/ 1983); Public Laws Authorizing BHPr Programs (96th Congress to date/ 1985); Reauthorization of Title VIII Nurse Education Authorities (99th Congress).
    - Health Professions Legislation: Publications, cont'd. (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: Compilation of Selected Acts Within the Jurisdiction of the Committee on Energy and Commerce, Volume I: Health Law.
    - Health Professions Legislation: Publications, cont'd. (Box-folder 003-004)
      Re: Reauthorization of Title VIII Nurse Education Authorities (100th Congress); Public Laws Appropriating BHPr Programs.
    - Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re: (Public Health Service History) Final Report of the Study Group on Mission and Organization of the Public Health Service; A Common Thread of Service/ An Historical Guide to HEW (Health, Education and Welfare); National Institutes of Health Almanac/ History of the Division of Nursing.
    - Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice (Box-folder 003-006)
      Re: Original typewritten manuscript by Dr. Henry A. Foley on Nurse Practitioners (History of and literature review).
    - Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice (Box-folder 003-007)
      Re: The Application of Primary Nursing in a Hospital Setting.
    - Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Partnership in Nursing for Education, Practice, Research; Collaboration in Education, Practice, Research: Report of an Expert Panel.
    - Miscellaneous Documents Related to Nursing Practice (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Miscellaneous items: Business card and name sign
- CNHI: The JoAnne Peach Papers, 8 boxes, 3.5 linear feet
  JoAnne Hutchinson Peach was born in Goldsboro, North Carolina in 1945. She received her B. S. N. in May of 1968 from West Virginia University School of Nursing in Morgantown, West Virginia. She graduated from UVA School of Nursing in August of 1973. She received her certification as a Nurse Practitioner from the UVA in May of 1976. In May of 1980 she became certified as a Family Nurse Practitioner. Since that time she has served as a valued member of the teaching faculty at the University of Virginia and at Virginia Commonwealth University. She has also worked for various health care providers and hospitals. Most recently, Peach has been a Family Nurse Practitioner in Culpeper County, Virginia.
  Peach has served on various committees during her professional career such as Area Health Education Center (AHEC), the UVA School of Nursing planning committee for Pharmacology for Nurse Practitioners and Curriculum Planning. She was president of the University of Virginia SON Alumni Association from 1986-1990. Honors she has received include the Virginia Division Pace Award, the Virginia Division Lifesaver Award and the Charlottesville-Albemarle Unit Special Award in 1986 & 1987 from the American Cancer Society. She is a member of the American Nurses Society, the Virginia Nurses Association and the National Organization of Nurse Practitioner Faculties. Her publications include: "Nursing and the University of Virginia - A Winning Combination," The College Digest - Schools of Nursing, Spring 1989, and "Building on a Tradition of Excellence," The College Digest - Schools of Nursing, Fall 1990.
  This is a well rounded collection of the papers of JoAnne Peach, formerly a Nurse Practitioner Instructor at the University of Virginia School of Nursing. The collection includes biographical information such as vitas, teaching evaluations, continuing education, correspondence, and papers from her own experiences as a student nurse. The collection highlights the professional and academic concerns of teaching Nurse Practitioners. It also highlights the experiences of a faculty member of the School of Nursing at the University of Virginia and includes handouts, correspondence, course information, and teaching aids. The political and professional concerns of a Nurse Practitioner are well represented with correspondence and white papers regarding legal and social issues from various organizations Peach was affiliated with. The professional papers created and presented by Peach at various conferences and workshops are in this collection. Her experiences teaching at other institutions such as the Virginia Commonwealth University School of Nursing and Piedmont Virginia Community College are also included. Well represented are the planning committees, correspondences and progress reports on UVA's Primary Care Consortium, Primary Care Education Committee, and Area Health Education Centers (AHEC).
  The collection has been arranged into four series: Series 1: Professional Career; Series 2: UVa School of Nursing and Nurse Practitioners; Series 3: Virginia Commonwealth University School of Nursing, Piedmont Virginia Community College, and Page County Consortium; Series 4: Publications, Media Clippings, and Presentations
  - Series 1: Professional Career
    - Biographical Information 1979-2001 (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Professional vitas, teaching evaluations, personal essays, memory scrapbook and awards
    - Correspondence to and from Peach 1975 to 2000 (Box-folder 001-002)
    - Student Nurse Papers c. 1972-1976 (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Nurse practitioner course syllabus, exams, handouts and reports
    - Student Nurse Papers 1974-1988 (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Issues, notes on birth control, abortion and rape, paper titled "To Have or Not to Have a Baby ... That is the Question!"
    - Student Nurse Papers, West Virginia University School of Nursing 1964-1973 (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Student handouts, course syllabus, forms
    - Student Nurse Papers 1972-1973 (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Teaching Practicum, Nurs 301, syllabus, course handouts, evaluation form
    - Career 1992-1993 (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Professional consultations, appointments, correspondence, lectures
    - Continuing Education 1975-1993 (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Diplomas and certificates
    - Career: Papers 1977-1997 (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: "Early Days of the Nurse Practitioner Program at the University of Virginia 1970-1976" by JoAnne Peach, and "To Everything There is a Season and A Time to Every Purpose Under the Heaven"
    - Presentations by Peach 1997-1999 (Box-folder 001-010)
      Re: "A Successful School of Nursing - AHEC Partnership to Improve Primary Health Care in Rural Areas", National Organization of Nurse Practitioner Faculties (NONPF) conference.
  - Series 2: Peach and the UVa School of Nursing and Nurse Practitioners
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Faculty 1982-1994 (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Handouts, correspondence, meeting minutes
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Faculty 1975-1992 (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Directories, course schedules and correspondence, Program Revision, reports, correspondence, statistics and meeting minutes
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Faculty 1993-1996 (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Seminar, "Teaching Pharmacology to Nurse Practitioners, guidelines, handouts correspondence"
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Faculty 1978 (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Workshop, "History and Physical Appraisal Skills," handouts, notes, and correspondence
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Nurse Practitioner Program 1980-2000 (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Articles, criteria, standards
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Nurse Practitioner Program 1987-1995 (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Recruitment, selection, preadmission
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Grants 1976-1981 (Box-folder 002-007)
      Re: Reports, correspondence, tables and statistics
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Grants 1985-1994 (Box-folder 002-008)
      Re: Reports, correspondence
    - Nurse Practitioners, Statistics and Surveys 1990-1994 (Box-folder 003-001)
    - Nurse Practitioners, Statistics and Surveys c. 2000 (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Role, job description, handouts, and publications
    - History of Nurse Practitioners 1990-1994 (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: "Interview with Co-founder of NP movement," NPNews, handouts, Nursing and Nursing Education in the United States, by the Committee for the Study of Nursing Education, Chicago, The MacMillian Company, 1923, "Public Health and the Civil War," The Sanitarians: A History of American Public Health Duffy, John, Urbana and Chicago, University of Illinois Press, 1990, (3) articles in Nursing Pub. On history of Nurse Practitioners
    - Nurse Practitioners 1977-2000 (Box-folder 003-004)
      Re: Rules and Regulations for Certification, Licensure, and Nurse Practitioner Standards of Practice, reports and publications
    - Nurse Practitioner Issues c. 2000 (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re: Reimbursement, insurance, risk management, federal assistance to the elderly, reports, handouts, and publications
    - Nurse Practitioner Program Graduates 1971-1987 (Box-folder 003-006)
      Re: Directories
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing, seminars 1979-1991 (Box-folder 003-007)
      Re: "Interviewing" and "Breast Exam," handouts, notes, outlines
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing, workshop 1978 (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Assessment of the Neurological Patient, notes and handouts
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing, lectures 1979-1997 (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Various lecture health information handouts
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing 1972-1997 (Box-folder 003-010)
      Re: Nurse Practitioners, students, handouts, brochures
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 550 1991-1996 (Box-folder 004-001)
      Re: Pharmacology: Course syllabus, handouts, notes and schedules
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 551 1990-1995 (Box-folder 004-002)
      Re: Health Assessment: Course syllabus, handouts, notes and schedules
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 566 1990-1996 (Box-folder 004-003)
      Re: Primary Care Seminar: Course objectives, handouts, notes and schedules
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 567 and 569 1991 (Box-folder 004-004)
      Re: Family Nurse Practitioner Seminar and Family Nurse practitioner Practicum: Course syllabus, handouts, and course evaluation sheet
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 594 n.d. (Box-folder 004-005)
      Re: Advanced Psychopharmacology: Course manual
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 800 1997 (Box-folder 004-006)
      Re: History of Nursing: Course syllabus, handouts, notes and schedules
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: GNUR 568, 570, 571, 572, 590, 760 1992-2000 (Box-folder 004-007)
      Re: Family Nurse Practitioner Practicum, Family Nurse Practitioner Seminar, Family Nurse Practitioner Preceptorship, Collaborative Role Development in Multidisciplinary Practice, Health Policy and Issues, Course syllabus, handouts, notes and schedules
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: Nurse Practitioner Clinical Rotation 1978-1997 (Box-folder 004-008)
      Re: Sites, schedules and correspondence
    - UVA School of Nursing Courses: Nurse Practitioner Clinical Rotation 1975-1996 (Box-folder 004-009)
      Re: Student information handouts, faculty assignments, guidelines and correspondence, course syllabus, handouts, notes and course evaluation forms
    - UVA School of Nursing - Nurse Practitioner Program 1975-1980 (Box-folder 005-001)
      Re: Course Material, handouts: generic
    - UVA School of Nursing - Nurse Practitioner Program n.d. (Box-folder 005-002)
      Re: Course Handouts: study guides and case study
    - UVA School of Nursing - Nurse Practitioner Program 1992-2000 (Box-folder 005-003)
      Re: Course Handouts, outlines, assessments
    - Presentation: "Key Factors in the Development of A Nurse Practitioner Educational Program: Evolution of the Nurse Practitioner Program at the University of Virginia," by JoAnne Peach 1997 (Box-folder 005-004)
      Re: Nurse Practitioner Conference Nov. 13 and 14th, Groningen, The Netherlands, paper, drafts, notes on paper, conference information and publications and correspondences
    - National Organization of Nurse Practitioner Faculties (NONPF) conference 1995 (Box-folder 005-005)
      Re: Keystone, Colorado, notes
    - Teaching Aids: Overhead Transparencies n.d. (Box-folder 005-006)
      Re: Head and Neck Exam
    - Teaching Aids: Overhead Transparencies n.d. (Box-folder 005-007)
      Re: Various Course Lectures
    - UVA School of Nursing Nurse Practitioner Collaborative Education 1993-2000 (Box-folder 005-008)
    - University of Virginia, Primary Care Consortium c.1994 (Box-folder 005-009)
      Re: Grant Proposal, correspondence, and reports and meeting minutes
  - Series 3: Virginia Commonwealth University School of Nursing, Piedmont Virginia Community College, Page County Consortium
    - Virginia Commonwealth University School of Nursing - Courses 1999-2000 (Box-folder 006-001)
      Re: 475, 488, 496, 682, 503, and 684, course syllabus; Nursing 511, course syllabus and handouts
    - Virginia Commonwealth University School of Nursing n.d. (Box-folder 006-002)
      Re: Student handouts, "Origin of the School of Nursing, Virginia Commonwealth University," author unknown
    - Virginia Commonwealth University School of Nursing 1992-2000 (Box-folder 006-003)
      Re: Faculty forms, meeting minutes, reports, guidelines
    - Piedmont Virginia Community College 1982 (Box-folder 006-004)
      Re: Nursing 226-01, taught by JoAnne Peach, course syllabus and handouts and correspondence
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Page County Consortium 1994-1996 (Box-folder 006-005)
      Re: Board minutes and correspondence, reports, "Virginia Care Foundation Executive Summary on Page Primary Care Consortium
    - University of Virginia School of Nursing - Page Primary Care Education Committee 1994-1996 (Box-folder 006-006)
      Re: Goals, meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence
    - Area Health Education Centers, (AHEC) Virginia 1993-1999 (Box-folder 006-007)
      Re: Publications, reports, and correspondence
  - Series 4: Publications, Media Clippings, Presentations
    - Publications 1978-1998 (Box-folder 007-001)
      Re: American Nurses Association, legislative handouts, "Medicare and Incident to Payment" Standards of Clinical Practice and Scope of Practice for the Acute Care Nurses Practitioner, copy of 31 page booklet, "Standards of Practice for the Primary Health Care Nurse Practitioner" copy of 11 page booklet, 1987, "Scope of Practice of the Primary Health Care Nurse Practitioner," copy of 11 page booklet, 1995, "You and the Law of the Gray Areas Of Practice," pamphlet, and handout 1978 conference AMA San Antonio, Texas, Salaries of Instructional and Administrative Nursing Faculty," 1998, Correspondence AMA, 1993 and 1996
    - Publications 1993 (Box-folder 007-002)
      Re: "Nurse Practitioners and Certified Nurse Midwives: A Meta-Analysis of Studies on Nurses in Primary Care Roles" by Sharon A. Brown and Deanna E. Grimes, American Nurses Publishing, 105 pages
    - Publications 1993 (Box-folder 007-003)
      Re: American Academy of Nurse Practitioners, "Standards of Practice," "Statement on Nurse Practitioners and the National Health Care Agenda" by Jan Towers, promotional brochures
    - Legislation Nov. 1993 (Box-folder 007-004)
      Re: "Advance Practice Nursing: Meeting the Primary Health Care Needs of Virginians" Report from the Nursing Task Force to the Joint Commission on Health Care, 56 pages
    - Publications 1988-1996 (Box-folder 007-005)
      Re: American College of Nurse Practitioners, handouts and brochure, National Association of Pediatric Nurse Associates and Practitioners, white paper, Educational Preparation and Role Parameters of Pediatric Nurse Practitioners" position statement, "Health Care Reform for Children," report, "1995, National Organization of Nurse Practitioner Faculties, statement paper, "Proposed Federal Budget Cuts Nursing Education Funds," technical report, "Nurse Practitioner Educational Programs 1988-1995, Workforce Policy Project, booklet, 1996, 41 pages.
    - Publications 1993-1996 (Box-folder 007-006)
      Re: 21 newspaper clippings from local newspapers regarding UVA - SON Nurse Practitioners Program or Nurse Practitioners
    - Legislation 1994 (Box-folder 007-007)
      Re: Virginia: Draft Issue Brief, "Optimum Use of Nurse Practitioners, SJR 164, Joint Commission on Health Care
    - Legislation 1979-1995 (Box-folder 007-008)
      Re: Virginia: Issues: Virginia Board of Nursing Regulations, Nursing Shortages, State Board Actions on 1979, SJR 179 "Primary Care Needs Assessment Summary of Findings, State Board Actions 1991, Medicaid Program 1992, Proposed Regulations Prescriptive Authority 1992, Senate Joint Resolution No 343, 1993 Health Sciences Center report for House Joint Resolution 512, 1995, correspondence regarding issues
    - Presentations n.d. (Box-folder 007-009)
      Re: "USA - Creating a New Role Partnering to Meet a National Need" and "Survey results comparing the NP Program in Virginia to Georgia," Neither of these are dated and author is unknown but presumed to be Peach.
    - Publications 1962-1985 (Box-folder 008-000)
      Re: American Heart Association:
      Part 1 Examination of the Heart: History Taking